A Guide to the Carl Van Vechten-Mark Lutz Collection,
Rare Books and Special Collections, Boatwright Library, University of Richmond
Rare Books and Special Collections, Boatwright Library, University of Richmond
Guide to the Carl Van Vechten-Mark Lutz Collection
Rare Books and Special Collections, Boatwright Library, University of Richmond
5
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mark Lutz, 1969
Biographical/Historical Information
Carl Van Vechten: author; born Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 17th June 1880; son of Charles Duane Van Vechten and Ada Amanda Fitch; marriage, 1st, 1907, Anna Elizabeth Snyder; divorced 1912; marriage, 2nd, Fania Marinoff, Russian actress. Died New York, 1964. Education: University of Chicago; Ph.B. 1903. Assistant musical critic, New York Times, 1906-7, 1910-13; Paris Correspondent New York Times, 1908-1909; editor of Programme Notes Symphony Society of New York, 1910-11; dramatic critic New York Press, 1913-14; contributor, musical biographies to revised edition Century Dictionary, 1911; Member Art Commission, Fisk University; Member of Board, Cosmopolitan Symphony Orchestra; W. C. Handy Foundation for the Blind, 1952; Life Member Negro Actors' Guild; Founder of the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters at Yale University Library, 1941 (awarded the title of Honorary Curator in 1946); Founder: Carl Van Vechten Collection of Books and Manuscripts at the New York Public Library, 1941; and also of the George Gershwin Memorial Collection of Music and Musical Literature at Fisk University, 1944; Founder of Jerome Bowers Peterson Memorial Collection of Photographs of Celebrated Negroes by Carl Van Vechten, at Jonson Gallery, University of New Mexico, 1955; Rose McClendon Memorial Collection of Photographs of Celebrated Negroes by Carl Van Vechten, at Howard University, 1946; Anna Marble Pollock Memorial Library of Books about Cats, at Yale University Library, 1947; Florine Stettheimer Memorial Library of Books about the Fine Arts at Fisk University, 1949; Captain at AmericanTheatre Wing Stage Door Canteen in New York, 1942-45 and at their Merchant Seamen's Club, 1943-45; Honorary Doctor of Literature, Fisk University, 1955; Member National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1961. Publications: Composer; Five Old English Ditties, 1904; Author; Music after the Great War, 1915; Music and Bad Manners, 1916; Interpreters and Interpretations, 1917; The Merry-go-round, 1918; The Music of Spain, 1918; In the Garret, 1920; A Letter by Morgan Lewis Fitch, 1920; Interpreters, 1920; The Tiger in the House, 1920; Lords of the Housetops, 1921; Peter Whiffle--His Life and Works, 1922; The Blind Bow-Boy, 1923; The Tattooed Countess, 1924 (made into a musical by Coleman Dowell, produced New York 1961; Firecrackers, 1925; Excavations, 1926; Nigger Heaven, 1926; Spider Boy, 1928; Feathers, 1930; Parties, 1930; Sacred and Profane Memories, 1932; Nijinsky, 1946; Isadora Duncan, 1947; Pavlova, 1947; Alfred A. Knopf at 60, 1952; Fragments from an Unwritten Autobiography, 1955; Gardenias for Alicia, 1960; Between Friends, 1961; editor Selected Writings of Gertrude Stein, 1946; editor Last Operas and Plays by Gertrude Stein, 1949; Photographer, 1932-64; (editor) Two: Gertrude Stein and Her Brother, 1951; Mrs. Reynolds, 1952; Bee-Time Vine, 1953; As Fine as Melanctha, 1954; Painted Lace, 1955; Stanzas in Meditation, 1956; and, finally, Book of the Alphabet and Birthdays, 1957.(See note 1 at the end of the guide.)
Mark Lutz: journalist/editor. Born Glassborough, New Jersey, 1901. Family moved to Richmond the following year where his father became editor of the Richmond News Leader. Living on Park Avenue the Lutz family and the Clarke family were next-door-neighbours. The young Emily Clarke was soon to become a founder member and co-editor of The Review, a literary magazine which achieved a certain degree of fame. Mark enrolled at the University of Richmond, where he lived on campus. He was graduated in 1923. Shortly thereafter he also joined the Richmond News Leader where he rose to become its book reviewer/critic. Subsequently, he wrote for both Richmond newspapers-the News Leader and the Times-Dispatch -as a book reviewer and theatre critic with a byline. Mark's elder brother, Earl, wrote also-a history called Chesterfield: An Old Virginia County, which became a textbook in the public schools in the Commonwealth. He also worked on a study of the Confederate Naval Academy and the students who absconded with the treasury, which Mark completed following his brother's death, although it was never published. It is not surprising, given this writing background that Mark too turned his hand to journalism. He moved to the Germantown area of Philadelphia in the mid-1930s, where he was for many years editor of the Philco News, and other industrial publications. Died Philadelphia, 1969.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes letters, photographs, magazine articles, and other memorabilia of Mark Lutz, Virginia newspaper journalist, and Carl Van Vechten, writer, photographer, and New York Times journalist and fine arts critic.
Contents List
- Photographic Portraits by Carl Van Vechten.
  - Louis Broomfield November 2, 1933 (Box 1:1)
    writer/publisher
  - Paul Vincent Carroll April 26, 1938 (Box 1:2)
    writer
  - Paul Gallico December 28, 1937 (Box 1:3)
  - Robinson Jeffers September 7, 1934 (Box 1:4)
    poet/writer
  - Robinson Jeffers September 7, 1934 (Box 1:5)
  - Robinson Jeffers September 7, 1934 (Box 1:6)
  - Sinclair Lewis June 5, 1938 (Box 1:7)
  - Mabel (Dodge) Luhan April 12, 1934 (Box 1:8)
    socialite/writer
  - Mabel (Dodge) Luhan April 12, 1934 (Box 1:9)
  - W. Somerset Maugham May 26, 1934 (Box 1:10)
  - Carlotta O'Neil September 5, 1933 (Box 1:11)
    actress
  - Eugene O'Neil September 5, 1933 (Box 1:12)
  - Julia Peterkin February 26, 1933 (Box 1:13)
  - Julia Peterkin February 26, 1933 (Box 1:14)
  - I. J. Singer January 7, 1938 (Box 1:15)
  - I. J. Singer January 7, 1938 (Box 1:16)
  - Gertrude Stein (at Bilignin) June 13, 1934 (Box 1:17)
  - Gertrude Stein (at Charvrottes) June 12, 1934 (Box 1:18)
  - Gertrude Stein (New York) November 4, 1934 (Box 1:19)
  - Gertrude Stein (in her lecture dress) November 4, 1934 (Box 1:20)
  - Gertrude Stein (in her lecture dress) November 4, 1934 (Box 1:21)
  - Gertrude Stein (in her lecture dress) November 4, 1934 (Box 1:22)
  - Gertrude Stein (in her lecture dress) November 4, 1934 (Box 1:23)
  - Gertrude Stein & Alice Toklas November 4, 1934 (Box 1:24)
    cookery-book authoress
  - Alice B. Toklas Nov. 4, 1934 (Box 1:25)
  - Alice B. Toklas Nov. 4, 1934 (Box 1:26)
  - Carl Van Vechten-writer, critic & photographer (self portrait) June 16, 1934 (Box 1:27)
  - Dr Lin Yutang October 29, 1936 (Box 1:28)
    writer & academic
  - Unidentified-(almost certainly Mark Blitzstein, composer) October 23, 1933 (Box 1:29)
  - Unidentified February 17, 1934 (Box 1:30)
- Photographs by Carl Van Vechten: Section devoted to Gertrude Stein, Alice B. Toklas, and Carl Van Vechten.
  - Stein, Toklas, Carl Van Vechten, Pilot and Stewardess on the boarding-steps prior to their first flight-Cleveland-Chicago Photograph by Dudley Brumbach, Cleveland Plain Dealer November 7, 1934 (Box 2:1a)
  - Gertrude Stein and Alice Toklas displaying good-luck fetishes prior to departure November 7, 1934 (Box 2:1b)
  - Carl Van Vechten and Gertrude Stein May 2, 1935 (Box 2:2)
  - Gertrude Stein (smaller print of No. 19 above) November 4, 1934 (Box 2:3)
  - Gertrude Stein and Alice B. Toklas November 4, 1934 (Box 2:4)
  - Alice B. Toklas November 4, 1934 (Box 2:5a)
    large, signed, portrais-souvenir of a visit to Richmond
  - Alice B. Toklas November 4, 1934 (Box 2:5b)
  - Gertrude Stein-with dedicatory inscription January 4, 1935 (Box 2:6)
  - Alice B. Toklas- with dedicatory inscription January 4, 1935 (Box 2:7)
- Photographs by Carl Van Vechten and others.
  - Edward Albee April 18, 1961 (Box 3:1)
    playwright
  - Marguerite d'Alvarez March 23, 1933 (Box 3:2)
    contralto
  - Judith Anderson January 5,1937 (Box 3:3)
    actress. Portrayed as Gertrude in Hamlet
  - Anthony Armstrong-Jones December 23, 1958 (Box 3:4)
    photographer; the first Earl of Snowdon-spouse of Princess Margaret, for a time
  - James Branch Cabell April 30, 1935 (Box 3:5)
  - Willa Cather January 22, 1936 (Box 3:6)
  - Willa Cather January 22, 1936 (Box 3:7)
  - Christopher Davis January 30, 1962 (Box 3:8)
  - Lukas Foss undated (Box 3:9)
    conductor
  - Lillian Gish April 12, 1937 (Box 3:10)
  - Martha Graham and Bertram Ross June 27, 1961 (Box 3:11)
    Dancers
  - Chaim Gross May 14, 1963 (Box 3:12)
    sculptor
  - Philip Johnson January 18, 1933 (Box 3:13)
    architect
  - Bruce Kellner May 5, 1953 (Box 3:14)
    educator
  - Lotte Lenya February 13, 1962 (Box 3:15)
  - Mark Lutz 1932 (Box 3:16)
    one time journalist,and extremely close friend
  - Jacob Marinoff *Date? (Box 3:17)
    writer/editor and father-in-law?
  - Alicia Markova May 15, 1963 (Box 3:18)
    prima ballerina
  - W. Somerset Maugham March 22, 1936 (Box 3:19)
  - Francisco Moncion November 30, 1944 (Box 3:20)
    dancer
  - Grace Moore January 5, 1933 (Box 3:21)
    soprano
  - Pierre Olaf June 7, 1960 (Box 3:22)
    actor, in La Plume de la Tante
  - Carlotta Monterey O'Neil September 5, 1933 (Box 3:23)
  - Eugene & Carlotta O'Neil September 5, 1933 (Box 3:24)
  - Eugene O'Neil September 5, 1933 (Box 3:25)
    writer/playwright
  - *Domingo Ortega June 5, 1935 (Box 3:26)
    bullfighter "Lester Zittreu at El Soto" on reverse--correction[?] made on typed list.
  - Edna Perker December 14, 1938 (Box 3:27)
  - Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings January 18, 1953 (Box 3:28)
  - Paul Robeson September 5, 1953 (Box 3:29)
    singer (bronze by Epstein)
  - 'Stage Door Canteen' Group April 8, 1943 (Box 3:30)
    (Busboy--Langston Hughes; hostess--Terry Keane; U.S. Seaman--Andy Meakes; and Canadian Seaman--J. H. Keller.)
  - George Szell January 5, 1954 (Box 3:31)
  - Paul Taylor January 12, 1960 (Box 3:32)
    choreographer
  - Pavel Tchelitcher November 14, 1934 (Box 3:33)
    painter
  - Andrew Turnbull April 18, 1962 (Box 3:34)
  - Carl Van Vechten (self-portrait) May 8, 1934 (Box 3:35)
  - Violette Verdy December 4, 1961 (Box 3:36)
  - Ethel Waters February 19, 1939 (Box 3:37)
  - Evelyn Waugh December 15, 1948 (Box 3:38)
  - Thomas Wolfe April 14, 1937 (Box 3:39)
  - Paul Bowles September 9, 1958 (Box 3:40)
    writer, poet & composer--with Carl Van Vechten (taken by S. Mauriber)
- Postcards and Postcard-sized Prints of Carl Van Vechten, his homes, wife, friends and acquaintances.
  - Childhood home of Carl Van Vechten at Cedar Rapids, Iowa No Date (Box 3(a):1)
  - Childhood home of Carl Van Vechten at Cedar Rapids, Iowa No Date (Box 3(a):2)
  - Carl Van Vechten (photograph by Hoppe) 1926 (Box 3(a):3)
  - Carl Van Vechten (photograph by Hoppe) 1926 (Box 3(a):4)
  - Norman Douglas (writer) and Carl Van Vechten No Date (Box 3(a):5)
  - Carl Van Vechten (plaster cast for bronze head by G. Lechais) 1931 (Box 3(a):6)
  - Caricature of Carl Van Vechten ("...the young 'un." By R. Barton) No Date (Box 3(a):7)
  - Fania Marinoff, Russian actress and future wife of Carl Van Vechten. 1903 (Box 3(a):8)
  - Fania Marinoff in Ada Van Vechten's wedding dress 1931 (Box 3(a):9)
  - Fania Marinoff's dressing table in her bedroom 1931 (Box 3(a):10)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: Drawing Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):11)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: Drawing Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):12)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: A corner of the Drawing Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):13)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: A corner of the Drawing Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):14)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: Victorian Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):15)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: A corner of the Victorian Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):16)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: A window in the Victorian Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):17)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: Dining Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):18)
  - Carl Van Vechten's New York apartment: A sideboard in the Dining Room early 1930s (Box 3(a):19)
  - (Carl Van Vechten in his home at Cedar Rapids, Iowa. Photograph by Kilborn[?] December 17, 1881 (Box 3(a):20)
    Van Cechten at 18 months of age
  - Diahann Carroll circa 1940s (Box 3(a):21)
    actress (in all probability taken by Van Vechten)
  - Paul Meares No Date (Box 3(a):22)
  - Paul Meares No Date (Box 3(a):23)
    Both of the above were taken with a backdrop of St. Mark's, Venice.
  - William Saroyan 1936 (Box 3(a):24)
  - Postcard photograph of bust of Carl Van Vechten 1931 (Box 3(a):25)
  - Photographs taken at Taos, New Mexico 1929-1930 (Box 3(a):*26)
    "Spud" Johnson, alleged to have been D. H. Lawrence's secretary for a short time, Mabel Dodge Luhan, and others. Those featured are identified on the reverse in Van Vechten's own hand:"Here is the Maestro with Tony Luhan and Weller Bynner. This taken at the corner of Mabel's in Taos-circa 1929-30."
- Carl Van Vechten; Articles, Reveiws, and Tributes to. about, of, and to.
  - Newsweek, (January 4, 1965), pp. 62-65. Article: 1965 (Box 3:1)
    "The Connoiseur," featuring Carl Van Vechten, and some of his great photographic portraits: self; Luise Rainer; Bill " Bojangles" Robinson; Paul Robeson; Grace Moore and Sir Laurence Olivier.
  - Cue (Manhattan edition), (April 9, 1949), pp. 18-19. 1949 (Box 3:2)
    "Carl Van Vechten--Novelist of the Twenties is now a Superb Portrait Photographer." A one column article accompanied by six of his photographs: Gertrude Stein; self-portrait; Bessie Smith; Mary Martin; F. Scott Fitzgerald, and Meg Mundy.
  - Issues [3 & 4] of The New Republic, 1955 (Box 3:3)
    (May 16, 1955), pp. 36-37. One of these has: *"For Marco [Mark Lutz] with love from Carlo, May 12 [?] 1955. New York[?]." Article by Edmund Laeders entitled: " Mr. Van Vechten of New York City,"an appraisal to mark his approaching 75th birthday on June 17, 1955. No photographs.
  - Issues [3 & 4] of The New Republic, 1955 (Box 3:4)
    As above, but no inscription.
  - Bulletin of The New York Public Library, Vol. 59, No. 7 1955 (Box 3:5)
    (July 1955.) Inscribed on cover by Van Vechten: "For my Baby as her getting-well, going away present, with all love from Carlo. August 29, 1955." Pp. 331-366, an article by John D. Gordon entitled, "Carl Van Vechten: Notes for an exhibition in Honor of His Seventy-Fifth Birthday." Photograph (self-portrait) of Van Vechten attired in top hat and formal dress together with buttonhole. Armed with cup and saucer.
  - Bulletin of The New York Public Library, Vol. 59, No. 7 1955 (Box 3:6)
    (July 1955.) Inscribed by Van Vechten on p. 331: "For Mark with love Carlo, July 30, 1955. New York."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 38, No. 4 1965 (Box 3:7)
    (April 1965). This number was a special publication marking the Dedication of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. pp. 156-159 are Van Vechten related.
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 38, No. 4 1964 (Box 3:8)
    Inscription at top of p. 156 reads: Inscribed by Van Vechten: "To Bino [? unidentified] with much love from Carlo, June [?]4, 1964."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 39, No. 4 1965 (Box 3:9)
    (April 1965). pp. 157-162 feature a Tribute to the late Carl Van Vechten by Lincoln Kirstein, entitled:"Carl Van Vechten (1880-1964)." Portrait of Carl Van Vechten by Romaine Brooks reproduced opposite, p. 157.
  - Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Letters, and the National Institute of Arts and Letters, Second Series, No. 15 1965 (Box 3:10)
    (1965). pp. 504-506; "Carl Van Vechten, 1880-1964," by Langston Hughes.
  - Phylon: The Atlanta University Review of Race and Culture, Vol. VI, No. 4 1965 (Box 3:11)
    (Fourth Quarter 1965). pp. 310-314 feature an article by Dr. Hugh M. Gloster entitled: "The Van Vechten Vogue."
  - Publishers Weekly: The American Book Trade Journal, Vol. 168, No. 3 1955 (Box 3:12)
    (July16, 1955.) P.178 has a photograph of Carl Van Vecten, Alfred A. Knopf, publisher, and Miss Texas Guinan [socialite? actress?] at the signing of the contract for the publishing of Van Vechten's novel, Parties by Knopf, 1930.
  - Loew's Weekly, Vol. 9, No. 36 1928 (Box 3:13)
    (May 21, 1928). Front page, under caption: "AUTHORS VISITING HOLLYWOOD FLOCK TO AILEEN PRINGLE'S SET!" Picture of "Mal St. Clair and Aileen Pringle 'read copy' on Carl Van Vechten's latest story when the popular novelist visited M.G.M. studio where the new Lew Cody-Aileen Pringle picture, 'Beau Broadway' is being made." [ This fascinating little period-piece publication contains a claim by the theatre owners to have installed the forerunner of air conditioning in their movie theatres--something to do with 'iced air flow.']
  - PLEASE NOTE THAT FOR THE REMAINDER OF THIS BOX NUMBERING COMMENCES FROM THE BOTTOM ON THE LEFT HAND SIDE.
  - Wagner Literary Magazine, No. 3 (1962). pp. 26-41 1962 (Box 3:1)
    contain an appraisal by John Schneider entitled: "A World of Whiffles: The Novels of Carl Van Vechten" Inscribed at top of first page of this article by Van Vechten: "This is not very hot, but it is jeune publicity.-Love to Mark from Carlo." Includes reproduction of a portrait of him by Romaine Brooks, and one of his own photographs of himself with Ethel Waters.
  - The American Record Guide, Vol. 26, No. 10 1960 (Box 3:2)
    (June 1960). pp. 776-777 carry a Tribute to Van Vechten by the Editor, James Lyons: "Evviva Carlo," on the occasion of his 80th birthday. P. 777 features a recent photograph taken of C. V. V. by Paul Mascriber, above which Carl wrote: "For dearest Baby Fania with all my on my eightieth birthday! Carlo, octogenarian. June 16 1960 New York." pp. 782-784 features an appreciation of Carl Van Vechten on his 80th birthday by Edward Jablonski, entitled: "Carlo Patriarch."
  - W. Somerset Maugham: Novelist, Essayist, Dramatist. 1925 (Box 3:3)
    With a Biographical Note by Charles Hanson Towne. New York: George H. Doran Company, 1925. P. 52 of this book contains a passage of very high praise of Carl Van Vechten's prose style by Maugham.
  - Jet, Vol. XVIII, No. 12. P. 40 1960 (Box 3:4)
    features a brief report on Carl Van Vechten's 80th Birthday Party: "New York's famous author-photographer-art patron Carl Van Vechten... ."
  - Bibliography: Pamphlets; broadsheets; prefaces; and a bibliography of books containing papers by Carl Van Vechten. No Date (Box 3:5)
  - Opportunity: A Journal of Negro Life, Vol. 4, No. 46. pp. 316-317, & 330 Date? (Box 3:6)
    review of Van Vechten's book Nigger Heaven by James Weldon Johnson entitled: "Romance and Tragedy in Harlem--A Review."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 35, No. 1 (July 1960). 1960 (Box 3:*7)
    Pages 17-22 carry a piece by Fanny Hurst [writer? academic?] entitled: "Zora Hurston [black authoress]: A Personality Sketch." P. 19 contains a flattering allusion to Van Vechten which he inscribed above and below with: "For dearest Baby this magnificent tribute.. .... all love from Carlo the happy octogenarian July 6, 1960. New York."
  - The Van Vechten Revolution, by George S. Schuyler. 1950 (Box 3:8)
    (Reprinted from Phylon: The Atlanta University Review of Race and Culture (4th Quarter 1950).
  - Postcard with ink sketch mailed in Milwaukee on August 22, 1950. 1950 (Box 3:9)
  - Blue cards Nos. 13 & 14 bumming up Carl Van Vechten. No Date (Box 3:10(a) & (b))
  - Gallery programme of an exhibition of sculptures featuring actress Fania Marinoff, and other thespians in leading roles. No Date (Box 3:11)
- Geometric-Patterned Box: Material by Carl Van Vechten.
  - Esquire: The Magazine for Men, Vol. VII, No. 6 (December 1962). 1962 (Box 4:1)
    pp. 170-174, & 256-258, feature "Portraits of the Artists," by Carl VanVechten. Those depicted: Henry "Homicide Hank" Armstrong, simultaneously World Boxing Champion in three weight divisions--feather-, light-, and welterweight; Alice Toklas & Gertrude Stein about to make their first flight; Salvador Dali & Man Ray, avante-garde artists--staring frightfully into the lens; Alexander Woollcott, ????; W. Somerset Maugham, writer; Carlotta & Eugene O'Neil, actress, writer/playwright; Marsden Hartley, artist; Billie Holliday, legendary blues singer; Henry L. Mencken, dictionary compiler and general know-it-all; and Madame "Bricktop, " Montmartre night-club proprietoress.
  - Ebony, Vol. V, No. 7 (May 1950). 1950 (Box 4:2)
    On p. 73 Carl Van Vechten is pictured at Fiske University's (Nashville, Tennessee) Carl Van Vechten Gallery on the occasion when the Alfred Stieglitz Collection was donated by his widow, the artist Georgia O'Keefe.
  - Vogue (incorporating Vanity Fair) (November 1, 1936). 1936 (Box 4:3)
    P. 67 sees Carl Van Vechten caricatured amongst a crowd of theatregoers attending a production of Macbeth in Harlem by an all-black caste. Article by Robert Littell entitled: "Everyone Likes Chocolate."
  - Golfer and Sportsman, Vol. 17, No. 101 (October 1935). 1935 (Box 4:4)
    P. 40, "Spud" Johnson, former secretary to the late D. H. Lawrence, and prominent citizen of Taos, New Mexico, photographed by Carl Van Vechten.
  - Harper's Bazaar, No. 2818 (80th year) October 1946). 1946 (Box 4:5)
    pp. 238, 353-356, article by Carl Van Vechten entitled:"The World of Florine Stettheimer" [primitive-impressionist painter]. Included is a portrait of him by Florine. Inserted beneath the title is an inscription by Van Vechten: "For Mark, November 7, 1946, Carl Van Vechten." Also in this issue--p. 166--included in 'The Editor's Guest Book' is a photograph of Van Vechten, together with a thumbnail sketch of that worthy.
  - Opportunity: The Journal of Negro Life, Vol. XVII, No. 2 1939 (Box 4:6)
    (February 1939). pp. 46-47, review by Carl Van Vechten of Mamba's Daughters, an all-black stage production-derived by Dorothy and Du Bois Heyward from Du Bois Heyward's novel of the same name. Carl Van Vechten is mentioned under 'Our Contributors' on the opening page.
  - Theatre Arts Monthly, Vol. XXIII, No. 4 (April 1939). 1939 (Box 4:7)
    pp. 271-278, "Actor Photographs by Carl Van Vechten," (listed in the order the portraits appear): Alfred Lunt; Ina Claire; Sara Allgood; John Gielgud; Ethel Waters; Judith Anderson; Lillian Gish; and George M. Cohan.
  - Dance Magazine, Vol. XXVIII, No. 9 (September 1954). 1954 (Box 4:8)
    pp. 30-31; 57; & 60-61 are Van Vechten related.
  - Rogue, Vol. I, No. 2 (April 1, 1915). pp. 8 ,9 & 10, short story by Carl Van Vechten entitled "How Donald Dedicated His Poem." 1915 (Box 4:9)
  - Dance 62, Vol. I (January 1963). 1963 (Box 4:10)
    " Dance 62 is a bonus offering for subscribers to Dance Perspectives a quarterly magazine." pp. 26-28 carry an article about Negro dancing by Carl Van Vechten, rather sloppily inscribed by him above the title and at foot of title page thus: "My title was 'Roses for Alvin'! With love to Marco from Carlo. Feb. 28, 1963 New York."
  - The Double-Dealer: A National Magazine from the South, published in New Orleans, Vol. III, No. 16 (April 1922). 1922 (Box 4:11)
    On pp. 185 & 186 is a review by Carl Van Vechten entitled: "Ronald Firbank."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 37, No. 4 1963 (Box 4:12)
    (April 1963). pp. 124-129. A humorous biography of one on the periphery of the Van Vechten circle, entitled, "Ma Draper," by Carl Van Vechten, with dedicatory inscription:"To dearest Baby Fania, with all my love, Carlo. May 3, 1963. New York."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 38, No. 2 1963 (Box 4:13)